Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is בבא בתרא Bava
Basra פ"ו, peh-vav, 86. We are eight lines down and we are
just finishing looking at a ברייתא baraita that speaks about dragging the
donkey drivers or the workers that are carrying loads into the house
of the buyer and when unloads the loads, then at what stage
are you קונה? koneh? The whole question about whether the vessels of
the לוקח lokei'ach of the purchaser are קונה koneh in the domain
of the buyer of the-
excuse me, whether the vessels of the purchaser are קונה koneh in
the domain of the seller. And similarly in this case of unloading
the loads from the donkey, if being in the bags of the
seller prevents the buyer from taking possession of them even when they're
unloaded into his property. So that was the discussion yesterday, but now
we're going to look at the end of that ברייתא baraita about
the question about that it matters whether the price has been set
or not. So let's take a look.
אמרי ליה הונא בריה דרב ששת לרבינא, Amrei lei Huna brei d'Rav
Sheshes l'Ravina, מכדי, Michti, let's take a look. פירקן קתני, pirkan katani,
once you have- it says that you have unloaded it. So מה
לי פסק מה לי לא פסק? Mah li pasak, mah li lo
pasak? So bracketing now this question about, you know, whose vessels they
were and so on and if that matters. Whatever it is, it's
talking that they're not anymore on the donkey driver and on the
worker, they're in the domain of the buyer and his קנין kinyan
works. So why does the ברייתא baraita therefore distinguish that it only
works once the price has been set? If the קנין kinyan is
being done and it's in his domain, why should it matter if
he set the price or not? So he gives the obvious answer:
אמר ליה פסק סמכא דעתיה לא פסק לא סמכא דעתיה. Amar lei:
Pasak, samcha daatei; lo pasak, lo samcha daatei. Once you have a
set price, then you have your, you know, final decision to buy.
Until the price has been set, you're not- you know, the guy
could double the price on you or the buy- or the buyer
could offer half of what you think is a fair price. So
nobody has agreed to the purchase until the price has been set.
All right, even if the מעשה קנין maaseh kinyan is being done,
that makes a lot of sense. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי תא
שמע. Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi: Tashma. Okay, so we're- we're still
in the middle of our discussion about כליו של לוקח ברשות מוכר.
keilo shel lokei'ach birshut mocher. So come in here. רב ושמואל דאמרי
תרוייהו, Rav u'Shmuel d'amri tarveihu, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both say:
כליו של אדם קונה לו בכל מקום, Keilo shel adam koneh lo
b'chol makom, a person's vessel if you're buying something and it's in
your vessel, it- it works in all domains. לאתויי מאי לאו לאתויי
רשות מוכר l'atuyei mai? lav l'atuyei reshut mocher? What is that coming
to include? Is it- wouldn't it be coming to include even in
the domain of the seller? So בכל מקום, b'chol makom, בכל מקום
b'chol makom that seems to answer our question that it works in
the domain of the seller. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכא
דאמר ליה זיל קני. Haca d'amar lei zil kani. You're right, but
it requires that the seller say go and take possession. So that's
a big concession, because until now it doesn't seem like it's either
definite yes or definite no: does it work in the domain of
the- of the seller? And here we're saying all that it requires
is that the seller indicate that he's prepared to allow the כלים
keilim to work. If so- if he says here, take possession, I'm
going to put it into your sack and you should now take
ownership, then it will work because the only thing that was preventing
the כלים keilim from working was that it was considered sort of
more being controlled by the seller since it was still like in
the seller's store. It was more under his control. So if he
somewhat relinquishes control and says I want you to exert your control
and you to purchase it, you know, then it will work. All
right, so that's a big concession, but that's what we're now saying.
So that's basically the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara that כליו של
לוקח keilo shel lokei'ach does not work in the domain of the
seller unless the seller says זיל קני zil kani go yes, I
want it- you to take possession now with your vessel. All right,
תנן התם. Tnan hatam. Now we're going to- that- that's really the
wrap-up of the discussion yesterday about כליו של לוקח ברשות מוכר. keilo
shel lokei'ach birshut mocher. We taught over there: נכסים שיש להם אחריות
נקנים בכסף
בשטר ובחזקה, nechasim she-yesh lahem achrayut niknim b'kesef b'shtar u'v'chazaka, things that
property that has liens, meaning real estate, you take possession with money,
paying the money for the property, writing the document that I- I
am selling you my plot of land, handing the document over, or
חזקה chazaka an- actual physical act demonstrating ownership, which we discussed in
a previous פרק. perek. ושאין להם אחריות, v'she-ein lahem achrayut, and things
that do not have- liens, meaning chattel, מטלטלין, metaltelin, אין נקנים אלא
במשיכה. ein niknim ela b'meshicha.
You can only take possession with them through משיכה. meshicha. Okay, now
that seems a little limiting because we know there are more- more
types of קנינים kinyanim for מטלטלין. metaltelin. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. בסורא מתנו לה להא שמעתא משמיה דרב
חסדא,
B'Sura matnu
la l'ha shmaata mishmei d'Rav Chisda, in בסורא Sura they taught the
following discussion in the name of רב חסדא Rav Chisda that we're
about to see. בפומבדיתא מתנו לה משמיה דרב כהנא, B'Pumbedita matnu la
mishmei d'Rav Kahana, in בפומבדיתא Pumbedita they teach it in the name
of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. ואמרי ליה משמיה דרב, v'amri lei mishmei
d'Rav, and some say in the name of רבא. Rava. This teaching
in this משנה mishnah in קידושין Kiddushin that chattel... Cattle you can
be קונה koneh *koneh* through משיכה meshicha *meshikhah*, so there was a
teaching in בסורא *Sura* or in בפומבדיתא *Pumbedita* based from different different
versions of who said it that significantly limited this idea that משיכה
meshicha. *meshikhah* is the generic קנין kinyan *kinyan* for chattels. Let's see
what they teach. לא שנו אלא דברים שאין דרכן להגביה *lo shanu
ela devarim she-ein darkan lehagbiya*.
When is it true that משיכה meshicha *meshikhah* works for מטלטלין *metaltelin*?
Only things that are not natural and normal to lift up, things
that are heavy that you gotta drag. Okay, then dragging is the
meaningful act of showing possession. אבל דברים שדרכן להגביה בהגבהה אין במשיכה
לא *aval devarim she-darkan lehagbiya behagbahah in bemeshikhah lo*. But things that
are natural to lift up, if it's like a can of soda
or something, then possession, natural possession is holding it and lifting it
up, not dragging it. So that can only work if the idea
that משיכה meshicha, *meshikhah* is meaningful is only in something in which
the more simpler and the greater demonstration of ownership of picking it
up is not the natural thing to do. Okay, so that's a
reasonable position although that wasn't said in the משנה mishna, *Mishnah*, but
let's see how that plays out. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this: יתיב אביי וקאמר לה להא שמעתא *yasiv Abaye veka-amar leh
hai shema'ata*. So אביי *Abaye* was telling over this teaching. איתיביה רב
Rav אדא בר מתנא *esvei Rav Adda bar Matna* לאביי *le-Abaye*: הגונב
כיס בשבת *ha-gonev kis be-Shabbat*. We have this teaching in כתובות *Ketubot*
about the principle of קים ליה בדרבה מיניה *kam lei bid'raba minei*
that if somebody does something that would incur a monetary liability at
the same time when they're doing an עבירה *averah*, the exact same
moment that they're doing an עבירה *averah* that makes them deserving of
lashes or certainly of a חיוב מיתה *chiyuv misah* deserving of death
penalty, that the more heavy penalty of lashes or the death penalty
overrides that sense of financial liability, and there is no financial liability.
If you're doing something so horrific, you shoot a gun and you
kill him and you get his clothes dirty, bloody. So the act
of the חיוב מיתה *chiyuv misah* act of killing him so overshadows
the other one that there is no liability for the other for
the monetary liability. Okay, so here's what it teaches: הגונב
כיס בשבת *ha-gonev kis be-Shabbat*, if somebody steals a wallet on שבת
*Shabbat* and takes it out into a רשות הרבים *reshut ha-rabim*, חייב
*chayav* you are liable to pay it back why שכבר נתחייב בגניבה
קודם שבא לידי איסור שבת *she-kvar nit-chayev bi-gneivah kodem she-ba lidei issur
Shabbat*. They're not coming at the same time. As soon as you
take the guy's wallet out of his hands or out of his
house, hopefully he's not carrying a wallet on שבת *Shabbat*, as long
as you pick up his wallet, that's הגבהה hagbaha *hagbahah*. Then you
did an act of גניבה *gneivah* because the act of גניבה *gneivah*
is defined by an act of קנין kinyan *kinyan*. And the חיוב
שבת *chiyuv Shabbat* is only when you step out with that wallet
from his house into a רשות הרבים *reshut ha-rabim*. So since they
do not come at the same time, you don't say קים ליה
בדרבה מיניה *kam lei bid'raba minei*. However, it continues: היה מגרר ויוצא
מגרר ויוצא *haya mgarer ve-yotze mgarer ve-yotze*, if instead of picking the
wallet off of his desk, you were dragging the wallet on his
ground in his house until you finally stepped out of his house
and dragged it into רשות הרבים *reshut ha-rabim*, in that case, פטור
*patur* then you're exempt from the liability of paying for the גניבה
*gneivah*. שהרי איסור שבת וגניבה באין כאחד *she-harei issur Shabbat u-gneivah ba'in
ke-echad* because it was simultaneous. You're dragging, dragging, you haven't done הגבהה
hagbaha *hagbahah*. The minute you take it out of his domain is
when you are now and from his רשות היחיד *reshut ha-yachid* into
רשות הרבים *reshut ha-rabim*, now you're חייב *chayav* on שבת *Shabbat* when
you pass over that threshold and now also you have effectively done
משיכה meshicha *meshikhah* because you've now taken it out of his domain
and brought it into רשות הרבים *reshut ha-rabim*. Now you might be
wondering how could you do משיכה meshicha. *meshikhah*, you can't do משיכה
meshicha *meshikhah* in רשות הרבים *reshut ha-rabim*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks
that question and there are a couple of answers, but a simple
answer is it is in the sides of רשות הרבים *reshut ha-rabim*
which are considered like the sidewalks which are considered like רשות הרבים
*reshut ha-rabim* for שבת *Shabbat* purposes but they're considered like a סימטא
*simta* for קנין *kinyan* purposes. All right, there are other answers, but
what's relevant for us is that it says that you're חייב *chayav*
when you drag a wallet, even though of course a wallet is
something that's natural to lift up and according to you משיכה meshicha.
*meshikhah* should not work in such a case. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says: והא כיס דבר הגבהה hagbaha, הוא *ve-ha kis de-bar hagbahah
hu*, wallet is something that you normally lift up, ואפילו הכי קני
במשיכה *va-afilu hachi kani bi-mshikhah* and it's even nevertheless it says that
it works by dragging it and that's when the שבת *Shabbat* and
the גניבה *gneivah* come at the same time. אמר ליה *amar lei*,
so he said back to him, אביי *Abaye* responded: במיסתא *be-mista*, I'm
dealing with a rope, you're dragging it, you're holding on to a
rope and you're dragging it with a rope. אמר ליה *amar lei*,
he said back to him, במיסתא אנא נמי במיסתא קאמינא *be-mista ana
nami be-mista ka-amina*. Who cares if it's a rope? Okay, even a
rope, you're dragging a wallet with a rope. So what? It's still
natural to pick it up. אמר ליה *amar lei*, no, במידי דבעי
מיסתא *be-midi de-ba'ei mista*. I meant that it's a huge wallet, somebody
should only be so rich to have such a huge wallet and
it's so heavy that you need like it's a big treasure. bag
and you need a rope to drag it. Okay, so I'm talking
about a suitcase full of cash, I'm not talking about a wallet.
All right, so again, that's a very weak אוקימתא. The simple sense
is a wallet, but he says we would be talking about a
case where it's not natural to pick it up, it needs to
be dragged, and that's why,
and that's why, because it's only natural to be dragged that משיכה
meshicha. does work. תא שמע, Ta shma, so we're going to try
to prove it again. ברשות מוכר לא קנה עד שיגביהנה או עד
שיוציאנה מרשותו, Birshut mocher lo kana ad sheyigbihena o ad sheyotziena meirshuto,
going back to our ברייתא, braita, which is why we're quoting it
here, that says that if you are purchasing something in the domain
of the seller, then you do not own it until you lift
it up or take it out of his domain. So it sounds
like the same object that you could be קונה koneh by lifting
up, you also can be קונה koneh by taking it out of
his domain, meaning doing a משיכה. meshicha, So once again it seems
like both are available. So the גמרא Gemara says אלמא מידי דבר
הגבהה הוא אי בעי בהגבהה קני ואי בעי במשיכה קני. Alma meidi
debar hagbaha hu ee ba'ei behagbaha kani ve'ee ba'ei bemeshicha kani. So
you see something that it says you can lift it up, so
it's natural to lift it up and nevertheless you also have an
option of being קונה koneh it through dragging it. אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק לצדדין קתני, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak letzitadin katani, מידי
דבר הגבהה בהגבהה מידי דבר משיכה במשיכה. Meidi debar hagbaha behagbaha meidi
debar meshicha bemeshicha. We're not talking about the same object, we're talking
about two options. You're buying something in the seller's domain, you can
be קונה koneh it. How are you קונה koneh it? Well, you
could be קונה koneh it by הגבהה hagbah if it's a thing
that you naturally pick up, or you could be קונה koneh it
by dragging it out of the domain by משיכה meshicha. if it's
a thing that you don't naturally pick up. So there are two
options but not the same options regarding the same object. Now the
רשב"ם Rashbam does note
that you could have just said that it's something that's natural to
drag, but you're קונה koneh it also if you pick it up,
right? Something that's natural to pick up, you're not קונה koneh it
if you drag. But it seems, and the רשב"ם Rashbam says that
this is the case although one could maybe debate it, that something
that's natural to drag, picking up, which is a real expression of
ownership, that would work even by like a heavy bag that's natural
to drag. So we could have said it was talking about that
case, assuming that that's true, that הגבהה hagbah. will always work even
when it's not the most natural thing. But then anyway, this is
the answer the גמרא Gemara gave. Sometimes הגבהה, hagbah. sometimes משיכה, meshicha.
depending on what is natural. All right, so again, the textual evidence
is all that you really have both options but we're making אוקימתות
okimtatos to establish this teaching. Now, continuing on פ"ו עמוד ב', peh
vav amud bet, תא שמע Ta shma coming here.
המוכר פירות לחבירו, Hamocher perot lechavero, so back to
our משנה, mishna. back to our משנה. mishna If you're
selling grain or whatever produce to your friend, משך ולא מדד קנה.
mashach velo madad kana. If you do משיכה meshicha even before you've
measured it,
once you've agreed to the price and you're buying a bag, so
now you just have to weigh it to figure out how much,
but even without weighing it, you're קונה koneh it once you do
משיכה. meshicha All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says והפירות דבר
הגבהה נינהו. Vehaperot debar hagbaha ninhu. When it says like פירות, perot,
produce, that normal produce is things that you can lift up and
it says משך mashach that you do משיכה meshicha. even though it
seems like something that the most natural thing to do would be
to just pick it up, like you take your bag of apples
out of the store. So the
גמרא Gemara says and it says it works with משיכה. meshicha So
the גמרא Gemara says no, הכא במאי עסקינן בשליפי רברבי. hacha bemai
askinan beshlifi ravrevi. We're talking about big bags. Okay, so since we're
talking about like a huge sack of potatoes, not three apples, a
huge sack of potatoes. And that's why it says that you're קונה
koneh with משיכה. meshicha So the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute,
אי הכי אימא סיפא, ee hachi eima seifa, but the end of
our משנה mishna, contrasted normal produce with flax. Okay, it says הלוקח
פשתן מחבירו, halokeach pishtan mechavero, if you're taking flax from your friend,
purchasing it, לא קנה עד שיטלטלנו ממקום זה למקום אחר. lo kana
ad sheyitaltlenu mimmakom zeh lemmakom acher. Then it's not enough to do
a simple משיכה, meshicha. you have to move it from one place
to the next. Now that was a really confusing line in the
משנה, mishna what really is the difference? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says
until this point we're assuming that both of these are cases of
משיכה. meshicha And what it's saying is, if you're buying a bag
of apples, so a simple move is משיכה. meshicha? But if you're
buying
a bag of flax, which is very, very long, then that type
of a thing, a little movement is not enough. You have to
literally fully like displace it and move it to another place. Okay,
so that's if you remember that was the whole debate of רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel about total displacement. Anyway, that's what we would
have
assumed that we were talking about. But now that you say that
even the case of the apples is a huge 20 pounds of
apples, so what's the difference between a big bag of 20 pounds
of apples and a big bag of flax? Why are you saying
one קנין for one and one for the other and a different
one for the other? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אטו פישתא בשיפא רבא מי לא עבדי? atu pishta bi-shifa rabba mi
lo avdi?
So the גמרא Gemara says and I don't get it like and
you know and so why would flax have a different scenario? If
you have a big bag of apples you could also have a
big bag of flax and since and if you gotta do a
משיכה meshicha by one you do a משיכה by the other there's
no way to contrast them alright if we were just talking about
a few apples so okay few apples but a few pieces of
flax are very very long we can contrast but once we're dealing
with huge sacks how are we contrasting them? So the גמרא Gemara
says שאני פישתא דמשתמט. shani pishta de-mishtamet. No no no flax actually
is different and there's different questions exactly how to read this but
you know the way the you know one reading the רשב״ם Rashbam
has is you can't make flax in big bundles in big bags
because it snips easily when you try to get a lot of
it together so therefore okay so what so what's the point here?
So the point is is that if you have a big sack
of apples or potatoes you know then you do משיכה. So when
you're dealing with flax you know in that case because it only
comes in small
bundles therefore therefore you know consistent with this approach since it only
comes in small bundles and it's natural to pick up you can
only do הגבהה hagbah and that's what it means מוציא ממקום זה
למקום אחר motzi mi-makom zeh le-makom acher somehow now means you have
to do הגבהה. hagbah So it's really hard to read the משנה
mishna regardless in terms of what the difference is with flax but
anyway now we are reading it rather than contrasting an simple משיכה
by a simple movement to a complete displacement because flax is long
we're contrasting a big bag of apples where you do משיכה to
flax which is only in small bundles and therefore you have to
do הגבהה. hagbah Okay
we're still at that. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי תא שמע קא
מיהא. Amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi ta shema ka mi-ha. בהמה גסה
נקנית במסירה והדקה בהגבהה דברי רבי מאיר. behema gassa nikneit bi-mesira ve-ha-dakka
be-hagbah divrei Rabbi Meir. Again a משנה in קידושין Kiddushin a large
animal like a cow you take or horse possession by handing over
the reins whereas a small animal like a sheep you do it
by dragging it you do it excuse me by lifting it that's
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar say. וחכמים אומרים ve-Chachamim omrim but the sages say בהמה
דקה במשיכה behema dakka bi-meshicha no a small animal you don't you
don't have to do הגבהה hagbah a sheep you could also just
drag it. Alright so now we're very concretely talking about a small
animal. So the גמרא Gemara says והבהמה דקה דבר הגבהה היא. ve-ha-behema
dakka bar hagbah hi. So a sheep is something you can lift
up וקתני דקני במשיכה ve-katani de-konei bi-meshicha
and according to the חכמים Chachamim it works to do משיכה. So
that seems to be pretty good proof so the גמרא says that
משיכה can work even by things that you pick up so it
says no שאני בהמה דסרכא. shani behema de-sarcha. An animal is different
because it like grabs hold tight to the ground meaning that what
does it mean that things you can pick up it's by הגבהה
hagbah and not by משיכה? Anything that's possible to pick up? No
things that are normal and easy to pick up so it's easier
to lead a sheep and to have it you know than it
is to you know lift it up although you always have that
image people carrying like the sheep around the shoulders or something but
anyway what the גמרא is now saying is this idea that once
הגבהה hagbah is possible then it has to be הגבהה is only
if הגבהה is the most natural and easy thing if it's difficult
like in this case of a sheep that's why משיכה can work
maybe that was actually the debate between the חכמים Chachamim and רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar.
Okay so that's the end of that discussion the assertion is if
הגבהה is possible in a reasonably easy way you have to do
it the evidence is against it but the גמרא at least defends
that position. Let's just do one more teaching here about relevant to
this idea of like when a sale is works and is final
okay going back to like selling produce in a store. רב ושמואל
דאמרי תרווייהו Rav u-Shmuel de-amri tarvaihu רב and שמואל Shmuel both say
כור בשלושים אני מוכר לך. kor bi-shloshim ani mocher lach. If somebody
says I am selling you a כור kor a כור kor has
30 סאה se'ah so okay I'm selling you like you know like
a huge I don't know gallon for $30.
יכול לחזור בו אפילו בסאה אחרונה yachol lachzor bo afilu ba-se'ah achrona
then you're measuring it out okay you know and you're pouring in
the ounces so even you know when you're at like 29
סאה se'ah each side can still reverse the sale isn't final since
you said I am selling you a סאה se'ah excuse me a
כור kor of grain so the unit is a כור kor and
therefore anything less you have not yet given him the object. If
you said to somebody I'm going to sell you an apple and
a pear for a dollar and he did a קנין on the
apple then it's not קונה yet because you're selling him the combination
it's one unit of an apple and a pear. Okay? So therefore
here too, it's a one thirty סאה *se'ah* unit, and until you've
measured out the full thirty סאה *se'ah*, even though it's in his
vessel, the סאה *se'ah* is not final. Now the רשב"ם *Rashbam* contrasts
this to the case
of where you haven't measured something in particular, but and the measurement
doesn't prevent the sale. But that's when you know what the object
is. I'm selling you a bag of apples, we know what the
price is, a dollar per pound, okay, and the only thing we
haven't done is we haven't measured it, but you have fully taken
the object that you are purchasing. In this case, since you have
not yet fully taken that object, the sale is not final, the
act of קנין *kinyan* isn't done on the full object, would be
a better way of saying it, and therefore both sides can reverse
it.
Okay. כור בשלושים סאה *kor bishloshim se'ah*, כור בשלושים סאה בסלע אני
מוכר לך *kor bishloshim se'ah besela ani mocher lecha*. However, if the
guy said, "I am selling you a כור *kor* for thirty dollars,
one dollar per סאה *se'ah*," then ראשון ראשון קנה *rishon rishon kanah*,
then basically
he's identified each סאה *se'ah* as a separate unit, and therefore every
סאה *se'ah* that is measured out, it goes into the vessel of
the לוקח *lokeach*, and the sale is final per unit. Because then
the units are each סאה *se'ah*. So the גמרא *Gemara*'s going to
challenge this. תא שמע *ta shema*, come and hear. אם היתה מידה
של אחד מהם ראשון ראשון קנה *im hayetah midah shel echad meihem
rishon rishon kanah*. So going back to this ברייתא *braita* that spoke
about ארבע מידות במוכרין *arba midot bemochrin* and it's saying if they
were borrowing the measuring cup, the measuring
vessel, then it's only sort of transfers whose vessel it is when
it's been totally filled up. But if it was, if you remember
that was the first case when it was neither belonging to the
owner to the buyer or the seller, was belonging to a third
party. Then you have to fill up the measuring vessel. However, it
says, if the buyer owned the measuring vessel, as soon as the
produce hits and goes into the vessel even if it's not filled
up yet, he takes possession. All right, now it's not clear why
this is such a question because who knows how it was framed,
it all matters how it was framed. Okay, but let's see what
the גמרא *Gemara* says. ואף על גב דלא נתמלא המדה *ve'af al
gav dela nitmala hamidah*. So you see it works even before
the measuring cup the measuring vessel has been filled up. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, כגון דאמר ליה הין בשנים עשר לוג בסלע אני
מוכר לך *kegon de'amar leh hin bishneim asar log besela ani mocher
lecha*. No, it's a case where he framed it that it's not
the whole quantity as one
unit, each sub-unit is also being identified. So he said to him,
"I'm going to sell you a הין *hin* for twelve dollars, for
twelve סלע *sela*, one לוג *log*
each לוג *log* for סלע *sela*." So since you've now identified that
the unit you're selling is not just the whole הין *hin*, the
unit that you're selling is each לוג *log* you're selling at a
סלע *sela*, and therefore every לוג *log* that hits, the guy is
קונה *koneh*. And now the גמרא *Gemara* says, אני מוכר לך *ani
mocher lecha*, וכדאמר רב כהנא שנתות היו בהן הכי נמי שנתות היו
במידות *ukedamar Rav Kahana shenatot hayu bahen hachi nami shenatot hayu bemidot*.
Like רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* said in a different scenario that we're
talking about there were like gradations like a standard measuring cup there
are lines at different levels. Here too there are lines at different
levels, and as the measuring cup is filling up, when it hits
each level, if you specified the price for those sub-units, then that
would be why each one is considered a separate sale and it
would work. Okay, we will end here.